When I started my career in finance, one
of my first big assignments was
delivering a 45minute investing 101 talk
to employees at a local tech company. I
got good feedback on the talk and I was
invited to keep coming back every month,
which I did for years. In many ways,
those talks early in my career were a
precursor to this YouTube channel. I'm
going to cover that same investing 101
information in this video. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to teach you
investing 101.
I'm going to cover why investing
matters, what stocks and bonds are, what
a sensible approach to investing looks
like, and what tools you should consider
using to implement these ideas. At the
most basic level, investing is important
because inflation is a real thing.
Inflation means that stuff gets more
expensive, measured in dollars over
time. Central banks in countries like
Canada and the United States target low
but stable inflation rates for reasons
beyond the scope of this video. The
important thing to understand is that
inflation should be expected. Meaning
that dollars held under your proverbial
mattress should be expected to lose
purchasing power over time. The same
number of dollars will be able to buy
less stuff in the distant future than
they buy today. This isn't a grand
conspiracy and the solution is actually
pretty simple. Don't hold dollars that
you plan to use in the distant future
under your mattress. That is at a
baseline why investing is important.
rather than under your mattress.
Investing your dollars into assets with
positive expected returns can generally
offset the effects of inflation and then
some. Stable investments like treasury
bills and high interest savings accounts
should generally be sufficient to keep
pace with inflation. Not always, but
generally. And investing in riskier
assets with higher expected returns can
help you on your way to becoming
financially independent. Financial
independence means that over your
working life, you save a portion of your
income, converting your human capital,
your ability to earn income by working
into financial capital, the ownership of
financial assets, eventually reaching a
state where you do not need to work for
money, financial independence. Let's
look at a couple simple examples to see
why investing matters. If you're 30
today, saving 10% of your income and
expect to earn a 7% rate of return on
your investments, you could retire at 65
and replace 60% of your pre-tax income
from your savings until age 95. That's
not including government pension
benefits like CPP and OAS in Canada or
Social Security in the US. If instead of
earning a 7% expected return, you earn
2%, which is a number in line with the
inflation rate in this simple model that
we're playing with, you would need to
save a little more than 50% of your
income. The difference between saving
10% of your income and 50% obviously has
huge implications for your lifestyle
today. One way to think about this is
that by taking on some risk to earn
higher expected returns with your
investments, you're letting the
financial markets do a lot of the heavy
lifting toward funding your financial
independence. That is the main premise
of investing. At a minimum, you need to
keep pace with inflation. And if you're
strategic about taking the right kinds
of risk at the right time in your
investing lifetime, you can use
financial markets as a very powerful
tool on the path toward financial
independence. The next important concept
is understanding what I'm talking about
when I say things like taking risk and
investing in higher expected return
assets. I'm not talking about trying to
pick winning stocks or getting ahead of
the next market trend. Two of the
largest and most practically relevant
types of assets, types of investments
for long-term investors are stocks and
bonds. Stocks and bonds are both
financial assets. A financial asset is
not a physical asset like a house or a
piece of gold. It is a contractual claim
on expected future cash flows. I'll
explain what that means, don't worry. A
stock is a piece of ownership in a
company. When you invest in a stock,
you're buying an asset whose value today
is based on the expected future profits
of that business. As a shareholder, you
participate in the ups and downs of the
company's successes and failures. If the
company does well, you can earn high
returns. And if it does poorly, you can
lose money or even lose your entire
investment. Stocks in aggregate have
performed well historically. Global
stocks have returned a little more than
8% annualized before inflation or a
little more than 5% after inflation for
the last 125 years. The stock markets of
some individual countries have performed
much better than the global average,
while others have performed worse. It's
important not to read too much into this
when deciding where to invest. For
example, the US stock market has
delivered huge returns in recent
history, but this will not necessarily
always be the case. The Japanese stock
market is a cautionary tale. From 1970
through January 1990, Japanese stocks
more than doubled the annualized return
of world excluding Japan stocks. over so
many years. That means that $1 invested
in Japanese stocks grew to $53.56
while investment in rest of world stocks
grew to only $6.72.
Japan had become a dominant stock market
at the time and it might have seemed
crazy to invest anywhere else. There
were narratives about Japanese
innovation and efficiency making them
economically unstoppable. However, if
you had invested in Japanese stocks in
January 1990, after that period of crazy
good performance, you would have $1.90
in August 2025, while the cost of
purchasing $1 of stuff that people need
had increased to $2.54.
This means that you lost money after
inflation over this period investing in
Japanese stocks. An investment in rest
of world stocks would be worth $22.94
over the same period. That Japan example
is for sure an extreme outcome. But
given the challenges in selecting which
country will perform well in the future,
holding a globally diversified portfolio
of stocks covering a cross-section of
the world's stock markets is generally
wise. It's common for investors to want
to invest in countries that have
recently performed well or avoid
investing in ones that have performed
poorly. But this performance chasing
behavior is more likely to do harm than
good. Past country performance does not
tell us much about future country
performance. Figuring out how much to
put into each country is another
interesting problem. But the good news
here, and this gets really interesting,
is that the market has answered that
question for us. The market is shorthand
for the huge amounts of buying and
selling of stocks that occurs around the
world every day. Each transaction in the
in the stock market contributes a little
bit of information into the price of a
stock. All that buying and selling
ultimately determines the value of the
companies traded on the stock market.
The market pricing machine assigns value
to companies based on things like their
expected future profits, their
riskiness, and how they behave relative
to other stocks in the market. In
general, more profitable and less risky
companies become more valuable, all else
equal, earning them a larger weight in
the market. Similarly, the combined size
of the companies in each country
determines that countries weight in the
global market. Those are called market
capitalization weights, and they're a
very, very good starting point for an
investment portfolio. In simple terms,
this means that you can look at the
relative size of each country's stock
market and allocate your portfolio
accordingly and you need a good reason
to be different from those weights.
Today, that means a large portion of a
market capitalization weighted stock
portfolio is invested in the US market.
All that said, taxes, costs, and the
currency that you spend your money in
could all be reasons to somewhat
increase the weight of your home country
relative to its market capitalization
weight. Too much home country exposure
is generally not a good thing, but some
overweighting of home country stocks
relative to their market capitalization
weights can be sensible. This will come
up when we look at some sample
portfolios later in the video. While
global stocks collectively have done
well historically, individual stocks
have been very risky. Many of them
perform poorly, often going to zero,
while a relative few of them have
performed exceptionally well. Picking
those exceptional winners ahead of time
is really, really hard to do. Similar to
not picking countries, it generally
makes sense to hold a diversified
portfolio of many stocks. Again, market
capitalization weights are a good
starting point. The good news is that
today there are lowcost investment
products that make it easy to buy a
globally diversified market
capitalization weighted portfolio of
stocks. It's important to mention that
even a properly diversified portfolio of
stocks can have violent ups and downs.
When your stock portfolio represents
your financial future, your financial
independence, it can be very hard to
watch its value swing wildly, which
makes stocks difficult for a lot of
people to invest in. Somewhat
paradoxically, that difficulty or
riskiness is exactly what makes stocks
good long-term investments. If stocks
were safer and their prices didn't
change much day-to-day, they would have
lower expected returns. Not everyone can
comfortably hold a portfolio of 100%
stocks. This is where bonds come in.
Bonds are loans made to companies and
governments. Instead of buying a piece
of ownership in a business, like with a
stock, with bonds, you're effectively
making a loan to a business or a
government. Unlike a stock, if a company
performs better than expected, its bonds
won't change in value much. And if a
company does poorly, its bonds still
won't change in value much. Even if a
company goes bust and its stock becomes
worthless, its bond holders may be able
to recoup some, not all, but some of
their value. Government bonds tend to be
even more stable. Bonds are still not
guaranteed investments and they come
with their own unique risks, but they
generally do not change in value from
daytoday as much as stocks do. In
finance jargon, finance speak, they are
less volatile. Bonds are less volatile
than stocks. While bonds are less
volatile than stocks, they also have
lower expected returns. That's the risk
expected return trade-off with stocks
and bonds. Bonds are also sensitive to
inflation. Periods of high inflation can
reduce the purchasing power of money
invested in bonds, which is a problem
for long-term investors. Stocks aren't
inflation hedges, but they do tend to
perform better after inflation than
bonds over long periods of time. Using
these two asset classes as building
blocks, you can create an investment
portfolio that matches your desired
levels of expected return and
volatility. A stockheavy portfolio
should be expected to be more volatile
and have higher expected returns while a
bond heavy portfolio should be less
volatile and have lower expected
returns. I am being intentional about
referring to stocks as being more
volatile rather than more risky than
bonds because risk is a pretty ambiguous
term. Volatility is certainly one way to
think about risk and commonly how it's
framed for investors. The risk of not
being able to meet your long-term
financial goals is another way to think
about risk. Some research has suggested
that from the perspective of meeting
your long-term goals, stocks may be
safer than many types of bonds despite
their higher volatility as long as you
can handle the ups and downs. Okay, so
these broad asset classes, stocks and
bonds exist and their expected returns
are useful tools to plan for the future.
It's not terribly complicated, but many
people have been taught that investing
means guessing and predicting.
Predicting which stocks or markets will
do well or predicting when to get out of
the market to avoid a crash. This
general concept of following the market
really closely in an effort to gain an
edge by guessing and predicting is
typically referred to as active
management. At the most basic level,
active management is the idea that you
can use your knowledge, your
information, to outguess the market,
resulting in improved performance. The
problem with this idea is that the
market's main function is aggregating
all available information, including
expectations about the future, into the
prices of stocks and bonds. The idea
that any one person or even team of
people can consistently outguess the
combined information production of all
market participants is kind of
far-fetched. An economist named Eugene
FMA shared the 2013 Nobel Memorial Prize
in Economic Sciences for his work on the
efficient market hypothesis which
formalizes the idea that prices are
pretty good representations of all
available information about stocks and
bonds. From the perspective of
investors, the people probably watching
this video, one of the best tests of
market efficiency, as FMA explained to
me when he was on my podcast, is whether
professional active managers can
consistently beat the market. If prices
do not reflect all available
information, if markets are not
efficient, a savvy active manager should
be able to learn things about a stock
that are not currently reflected in the
price and profit from trading on that
information. What we see in practice is
that only a small percentage of
professional active managers are able to
outperform the market and even the ones
that do outperform over one period
rarely go on to continue outperforming
in the future. This makes it very hard
to pick winning managers before the
fact. I would also say that this extends
to individuals trying to devise their
own active investment strategy.
Sometimes active managers get thrown
under the bus. Uh people make excuses
like well they can't because of their
fees or they can't because their funds
are too large. But very few individual
investors beat the market. I think the
same concepts apply to both professional
active managers and individual
investors. The alternative to active
management is typically referred to as
index investing. An index is a
representation of a stock market. In
Canada, we have the S&P TSX composite
index. The US market has a whole bunch
of different indexes tracking it, but
most people are familiar with the S&P
500 index. These are groupings of stocks
that have been put together by a
research firm, in these cases by S&P, to
be a representation of a country's stock
market. These indices are market
capitalization weighted, meaning that
larger companies get a larger weight in
the index than smaller companies. Since
they simply hold stocks as they exist in
the market, they're often used as the
benchmark for active managers. It's
basically like an index is like what if
you just did nothing? What if you just
took the market values of stocks and
held them like that? And so it's it's an
obvious comparison to an active manager
who's trying to do something. So the
index are used as a benchmark for the
active managers. Now an index is not
itself an investment. It's a
representation of a market. But there
are funds that rather than trying to
beat the market simply invest in the
stocks in the index in an effort to
capture the market's returns. Index
funds were first created in the 1970s
based on the observation that active
managers were not delivering index
beating returns. The other issue that I
haven't mentioned yet for active
management is that to do all of the
analysis and other work that's required
to run an actively managed fund that
tries to beat the market. These funds
have to charge higher fees and even
small fees in investing matter a lot due
to compounding over long periods of
time. If we think back to the earlier
example of saving 10% of your income for
retirement and earning a 7% expected
return on your investments, if you pay
an extra 0.64% 64% in fees. That's the
average fee difference between fee based
active funds and index funds in Canada.
And you don't earn higher returns in
exchange for the higher fees. You would
need to save 12.5% of your income or 25%
more to have a similar long-term outcome
to the cases I talked about earlier. If
the active fund that you choose
underperforms by more than its fees,
which is often the case since it's so
hard to pick winning stocks before the
fact, the numbers will look worse still.
When you sit down with a financial
adviser, they may well be able to show
you a list of actively managed funds
that have outperformed, making active
management seem compelling. But the
problem here is that over any 10-year
period, for example, less than half of
actively managed funds survive. The
remainder close or get merged with other
funds. Funds that merge or close tend to
be poor performers that have failed to
attract investors, which is why they are
closing or merging. This creates a
problem of survivorship bias. The sample
of actively managed funds that exist at
any point in time are not a good
representation of the performance of
actively managed funds in aggregate when
survivorship bias is accounted for. The
other problem is that funds that perform
well and survive in one period are no
more likely to continue winning in
future periods. Index funds take the
guesswork out of investing and make it
accessible to anyone. You don't need to
know how to analyze companies or predict
the economy or identify successful
active managers before the fact to be a
successful index fund investor. You
don't even need to be interested in the
stock market. You just need some
baseline knowledge about index funds and
enough conviction in your chosen
strategy and your chosen portfolio to
stay disciplined through inevitable
difficult market conditions. That point
is really important. You have to be able
to stick with whatever you decide to
invest in. To put this information into
practice as opposed to just talking
about it from a theoretical perspective,
we need to talk about investment
products. In 2018, Vanguard launched the
first asset allocation ETFs in Canada.
An ETF is an exchangeraded fund, which
is a fund that you purchase on a stock
exchange like you would purchase a
stock, but it gives you exposure to a
diversified portfolio of assets and you
you pay a fee to own it. Asset
allocation ETFs are now offered by a ton
of different financial companies in
Canada. We're going to look at one of
Vanguard's ETFs so that you can see what
I'm talking about. VGRO is the Vanguard
Growth ETF portfolio. It holds a US
total market index ETF, a Canadian total
market index ETF, a developed markets
excluding North America index ETF which
covers countries like Japan, the UK,
France, Germany, Switzerland, Australia,
and a whole bunch of others. And an
emerging markets index ETF covering
China, Taiwan, India, and a whole bunch
of others. And also three bond ETFs
covering Canadian, US, and global
excluding Canadian and US bonds. The
overall portfolio consists of 80% stocks
and 20% bonds. Canada in this portfolio
receives a much higher weight in the
fund than its market capitalization
weight. Canada's about 3% of the global
market and it makes up about 30% of the
equity portion of this portfolio. Now,
that is a deliberate decision by
Vanguard reflecting an intentional home
country bias which may be appropriate
for Canadians. I've got a video on that
if you want to learn more about why that
is. Vanguard has also created asset
allocation portfolios for more
conservative and more aggressive asset
allocations allowing investors to choose
the product that makes sense for them.
Since Vanguard had success with those
products, uh Beimo, RBCI shares, TD,
McKenzie, and and other companies too
have have launched similar asset
allocation products. An important point
is that these asset allocation ETFs are
rebalanced for you. Rebalancing is the
action of keeping your portfolio's asset
allocation targets in check as markets
change over time. For example, if you
were to build your own ETF portfolio
with the same underlying ETFs as VGRO,
you would need to keep an eye on the
weights of each fund. If the US market
does particularly well over some period,
it would end up making up more of your
portfolio than you had initially
intended it to. To resolve this, you
need to buy more of the other ETFs or
sell some of the US equity ETF or
whatever. Rebalancing is not
insurmountable, but it's it's work. It's
real work that needs to be done and it
often requires some math and a
spreadsheet. Asset allocation ETFs take
that off your plate and they and they do
the rebalancing for you, which is pretty
incredible and it makes investing just
that much easier and that much more
accessible. VGRO is just one example,
but each individual would need to choose
an asset allocation or an asset
allocation product that has the mix
between stocks and bonds that makes
sense for their behavioral loss
tolerance, their ability to take risk,
and their financial goals. I've also got
a whole video on that topic on asset
allocation if you want to learn more
about that. Investing is important
because it combats inflation at a
baseline and when some risk is taken, it
offers the expectation, not the
guarantee, but the expectation of
growing your wealth above inflation for
your future financial independence. The
two main asset classes to think about,
at least at the 101 level, are stocks
and bonds, both of which are financial
assets. Stocks are more volatile and
have higher expected returns, while
bonds are less volatile and have lower
expected returns. Depending on your
goals and your ability to withstand the
volatility of your investments from day
to day, you can arrive at some mix of
stocks and bonds that make sense for you
specifically. People tend to believe
that successful investing requires
understanding the stock market, the
economy, and individual companies in
order to guess and predict what to
invest in and when to get in and out of
the market. But decades of research
suggests that these are fool's errands.
Successful investing simply requires
capturing the returns that financial
markets have to offer, which can be
accomplished using globally diversified,
lowcost index funds. This is achievable
in Canada today with the many low fee
asset allocation ETFs that we have
available to us. Thanks for watching.
I'm Ben Felix, chief investment officer
at PWL Capital. If you enjoyed this
video, I discussed the same topic in
episode 381 of the Rational Reminder
podcast with Dan Bordalotti, aka the
Canadian couch potato, the OG of index
investing education in Canada. You
should check it out.